<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>My life rants</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Using Pelican to deploy static website in Gitlab.</title><link href="/free-society/2015/12/23/using-pelican-to-deploy-static-website-in-gitlab/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-12-23:free-society/2015/12/23/using-pelican-to-deploy-static-website-in-gitlab/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I my last article I wrote about gitlab pages.
This article is a quick note on how to deploy your static blog using pelican.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is a more developer /  computer known person prespective. If something goes wrong do ping me&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steps :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sign up for an account at gitlab.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new project called blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the GNU/Linux terminal and follow the steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sudo dnf install python-pip (Fedora) or sudo apt-get install python-pip (Debian)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sudo pip install virtualenv&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cd ~/Documents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git clone https://gitlab.com/your_username/blog.git&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;virtualenv blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cd blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;source bin activate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pip install pelican markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pelican-quickstart .Once you hit this command,enter the details of your site name and description. Go with the defaults for the rest of the things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cd content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create a file called first-blog.md (or any name). Write content following this pattern http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.6.3/content.html&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cd ../&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;type the command "pelican" . Once this command is done, you should have a folder called output. If that has generated, proceed, else hold up and cross check any errors or missed steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create a file called .gitlab-ci.yml and enter the following contents in it.
"""
pages:
  stage: deploy
  script:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mkdir .public&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cp -r output/* .public&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mv .public public
  artifacts:
    paths:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;public
  only:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;master
"""&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git add .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git commit -m "Blog on gitlab"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git push&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are done. If all go good, you should see the build starting in your projects build page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now sit back and relax until the build completes. Once done, you should see your website live at your-username.gitlab.io/blog&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for a ready repo, have a look at the &lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/voidspacexyz/pages/tree/master"&gt;sample repo&lt;/a&gt; I have put up&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have a sample blog running &lt;a href="http://voidspacexyz.gitlab.io/pages"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have written it better, send me a PR :-)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[free-society"></category><category term="gitlab"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="static_website]"></category></entry><entry><title>Static Websites on Gitlab</title><link href="/free-society/2015/12/23/static-websites-on-gitlab/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-12-23:free-society/2015/12/23/static-websites-on-gitlab/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Most of you might have been using a website called github.com for hosting your code repos. For those of you who dont know what is github, it is basically a website that offers, a version control system. Github also offers free unlimited "public" code hosting. And then if you want private code hosting, you have to pay and use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great so what is wrong with github.com now.
It is a simple answer. github is not a free software. If you dont know what is a free software, read about it &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.en.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.fsf.org/about/what-is-free-software"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why should I care if a hosted service is a free software or not ?
Simple, "Free Software requires Free Tools". More about it &lt;a href="https://mako.cc/writing/hill-free_tools.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon some research, I came across something called &lt;a href="https://gitlab.com"&gt;Gitlab&lt;/a&gt;. Gitlab is a free software, both in terms of code and in terms of hosting. We can have our own hosted version of the code or simply take the code and deploy it in our own servers. And another amazing thing I felt about gitlab was, it has taken some of the best features of github, bitbucket , gitorious etc and put them all together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for a long time, I have been missing one of the best features of github. It is called github-pages. It was the only reason I really didnt want to move out of github, if any of my project needed a website ? I didnt have the resource to host a website on a paid service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But alas to my happiness , gitlab on 22-Dec introduced gitlab-pages to its EE. So which meant, gitlab.com will have gitlab pages, where I could run website for my projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some more links, where you can find the official documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://doc.gitlab.com/ee/pages/README.html"&gt;Gitlab Pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/gitlab-examples/pages-plain-html"&gt;Writing plain html to deploy websites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/gitlab-examples/pages-plain-html"&gt;using jekyll to deploy sites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a python person, and already in love with pelican, &lt;a href="/free-society/2015/12/23/introducing-gitlab-pages/," title="link"&gt;go ahead here&lt;/a&gt; to use pelican to deploy your blog.
Belive me pelican is a much better tool then jekyll. Here is a article from @arunrocks justifying &lt;a href="http://arunrocks.com/moving-blogs-to-pelican/"&gt;why pelican&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now go ahead and explore Gitlab at gitlab.com&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[free-society"></category><category term="gitlab"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="static_website]"></category></entry><entry><title>Upar wala shab dek raha hai</title><link href="/life/2015/12/22/upar-wala-shab-dek-raha-hai/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-12-22:life/2015/12/22/upar-wala-shab-dek-raha-hai/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;First of all, let me just me translate the title "The one above will look after everything".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting right ? But the question is who is the "one above "? Above whom ?? Who is that ? What is "the one" got to do with us ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well to answer all these questions, lets go back to an old topic which stirred even AIB to do a long video to explain public that they should take an action. Yep, if you have guessed it right, you are awesome, else we are taking about "Net Neutrality"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following is the discussion that took place between Me and My friend on the same topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, I know about it. It is about "No discrimination between websites" and "all websites being treated equally" right ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes Man, In short, "All the internet traffic is to be treated equally with no discrimination".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, some of friends sent an email to the govt and they leaked all the  email-id's I suppose :-(,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, thanks to your friends for sending it. I really cant help with the leak. I was also affected by that. But wait, the fight is not over. It is just taken another turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, Is that thing not completed yet ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No Man, Sometime back the awesome facebook introduced something called "internet.org" in the aim of connecting the world with facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well that was an awesome move, they claim to say about 2 billions are still not on facebook and they want to enable them to be online soon. I mean this is really nice, a great effort I would call. The only bad move I would call was, they went ahead with reliance, which already gives "Free Facebook Pack", in places where there is no tower at all (which is literally most of the places).
Anyways a good buisness decision. To continue on with the story, a lot of people opposed it in the name of all knowing god "Internet", and then facebook made another decision recently called, "Free Basics".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well , I know about internet.org dude, I read an article about it. they say free basic internet for everyone, But what is this free basics ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing, plainly "internet.org" renamed. Dead simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok Dude, so what is with "Free Basics" now ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple. It shouldn't exist in the best interest of "YOU" ...!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, What ??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know Man, let it not exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok hold on dude, Why ??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well I would say, prove why do you need !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, Its awesome right, I dont need to pay to reliance anything, and I can still access facebook and a few apps for free. Its awesome, I dont need to pay anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to make you understand, let me explain what "Free Basics" is doing. Ok, so by default, Facebook is free of cost. Till then its all awesome,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now lets say, you have a website. Even if you dont, just assume you have one. Now your website is available on the internet.Right ? No matter if they use facebook or not, no matter which part of the world they are in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now with "Free Basics" you have to make sure your website also has to be available on "Free Basics".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What ? Ooh ! Is that going to cost me ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, No. If "free of cost".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phew ! For a monent I though, will facebook make me pay in "$'s" ?  Ok,Great, So how do I apply for that ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey ! hold on, dont do that. Dont register your website on "Free Basics".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Why ? ? Its free right ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes it is free, but not free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, Dude ! you are confusing me now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, lets take a different example. Out of "Free Basics" for sometime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets say, I will buy you a beautiful 2BHK in the heart of Bangalore. All costs paid by me. And let you stay in that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, Why would you even do that ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because, you dont own a house. Its simple, and since I have a lot of money, I would like to invest it in your home, so that you can enjoy living in that house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks Dude, You are an awesome friend, shall we disucss which part of the city are you going to buy this in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, I still havent finished my offer. I have a few conditions. But I am happy that you are already so exited with the offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, So what are your conditions ? Whatever they are , make sure it is also a fully furnished house. You know since you are paying the bills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, here are my conditions,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be CCTV setup in every room of the house, so that we can make sure your house is safe all the time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are allowed to use only 2 buckets of water everyday, that too cold water only. Water is in scaricity you know. So ...!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are supposed to take my permission if you are going to step out of your house. If I dont swipe the entrance card, you door wont even open. I will be your bodygaurd. Just so that you are safe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are only supposed to use the smart phone, I will give you, so that I can monitor your calls. Why ? Because, if you get all these spoof calls, we can handle them accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can only eat what I say you to eat and watch movies which I suggest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subject to change anytime without your notice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are not supposed to break any of the rules and if you break, you will kicked out of the house.
Hope you are ok with the conditions, let me get the paper work done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, seriously ? You are restricting me dude. I am a free person. I can do anything I want. I can wonder anywhere I like to. Why are your restricting ??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, Look, these are the conditions on which I will buy you a "Fully Furnished 2BHK " in the heart of Bangalore. Cumon Man, its an awesome offer, dont let the conditions stop you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me think about it dude, the CCTV monitoring is ok at the entrance, but why everywhere inside the home ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, cumon, your saftey and privacy is my first priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but Dude, My GF will comeover sometimes, and CCTV is kinda disturbing our privacy dude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh my god, Forgot one more condition. If anybody is to visit you, they first have to call me, and then do a registration in my portal, and then take an appointment and then after approval is only when, they will even be allowed to ring your door bell. Also note that, anybody visiting will be full searched and mined for every information that we can get to make sure that they are of no security issue for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What ??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[A few more restriction discussions on]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, this is too bad dude, Let me think about it and let you know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure Man, take your own time, but the offer will close in the next 5 min.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, I deny your offer. I cant be your slave just for a 2BHK house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, Are you sure ? 2BHK free of cost buddy. Who is going to offer you ? Seriously ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, forget it. I dont want it. I am rather happy with the way I am right now. I might not have to many things, but I am happy and free. I dont want somebody to rule me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hm ! Great Man, If you dont want somebody to control your personal life, why are you accepting somebody controlling your digital life ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude ! What are you talking about ? Who is controlling my digital life ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, the large corporation who have all the data of yours, facebook which is saying "internet is facebook" with their "Free Basics" , Aircel, Airtel and other telecos with their free whatsapp/facebook packs. You are sending all your data and information through their gateways.And they own your data. they can do anything with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, Now I understand why you gave me the 2BHK offer, I though you were serious. So you mean to say, with "Free Basics", all the websites will be loaded through facebook and they are trying to establish their monopoly in the internet space ??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exactly Man, they are basically creating a walled garden. the internet will become too restrictive with "Free Basics". We might all feel that, they are giving me all the websites I need for free, but when happens when your needs change ? What happen when you want to explore something outside the walled garden ? Children below 18 are not even legally allowed to be on facebook, what about them ? what if a website you want to visit is outside of "Free Basics" ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, your condition no 3. I have to take facebook's permission to go outside the walled garden. That is bad. I didnt quite realize it this big. They are trying to establish a large scale monitoring system over the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exactly Man, you are right. Now say, isin't this bad for a "Freedom society" ? Aren't we being restricted ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes Dude, you are right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, All the condition I put, is what facebook will put on "Free Basics". Repace me with facebook and yourself as the enduser. the whole story still applies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, Is there something I can do to clean off this crap ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yep, the simplest thing is to go to &lt;strong&gt;"http://www.savetheinternet.in/"&lt;/strong&gt; and send out an email to TRAI. Also facebook is doing this ad campaign asking everyone to support "Free Basics". Write to facebook that you dont want "Free Basics" in India. Also I will share a few images, that you can change your fb profile and cover picture as.
Talk to your friends, explain them the issue. Ask them to do the same. It is a very small effort you and me can do. But when all these collectively small efforts go through, only then can we expect a bigger outcome. An outcome that dosent affect the society, common man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, this is amazing dude, I will do that. But I have one more question. All this net_neutrality and things are ok for people like you and me. What about the people that facebook is really talking about. They are really out of the digital society right ? Something like "Free Basics" is really going to help them understand what the internet is like right ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now Man, that is a seroious question. This is what we call "Digital Divide". But here is a question back to you, if more people are not connected, then isin't the govt supposed to take actions to connect them ? Isint something like digital India be aimed at things like this ? We have laws and sections that can help India go digital. I am not aware of the exact sections , but I know people who can throw more light on that. If you are interested I will put you in touch with them.
Also what we need to remember is, Internet should be a tool for development of a society, not a walled garden of information. Would Mark have invented "Facebook" if he were given an internet like "Free Basics".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude, now that is another serious question. He surely would not have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exactly, "Free Basics" is not about connecting people, it is about making a better buisness around the not connected people. Facebook dosent charge anybody at all. But still they are valued at a few billion dollars. What makes them so much important. It  is data. They now want more data. the more the data, the more the money for them. So never fall for these traps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks a lot Dude, I am really not going to support "Free Basics".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank my friend, who dosent want to be named, for letting me write through our conversation here.
I would also like to thank Prasanna Venkatesh of FSHM (Free Software Hardware Movement, Puducherry) for that from his blog which gave me a quicker understanding of what is going wrong with "Free Basics"
 &lt;a href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/revolt-against-free-basics.html" target="_blank"&gt;Click here for the article on his blog&lt;/a&gt;. Do read through his article.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[freedom_internet"></category><category term="internet"></category><category term="net_neutrality"></category><category term="]"></category></entry><entry><title>The typical Mistake in a FizzBuzz Problem</title><link href="/technology/2015/12/18/the-typical-mistake-in-a-fizzbuzz-problem/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-12-18:technology/2015/12/18/the-typical-mistake-in-a-fizzbuzz-problem/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is one such interview question that no fresher has answered right in the first attempt. After about taking a few 10 interview candidates at my workplace, I am actually suprised. I was able to get it right the fist attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the question ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write a program that prints the numbers from 1 to 100. But for multiples of three print “Fizz” instead of the number and for the multiples of five print “Buzz”. For numbers which are multiples of both three and five print “FizzBuzz”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is a simple question, but a lot of them get it wrong the first time. So what do people write as solutions ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Fizz&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;elif&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Buzz&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;elif&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;FizzBuzz&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well this is the code, that all the people I have talked to have written in their first attempt. I used to actually be surprised initially but then I started expecting this answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is wrong here ? What are we to learn from a code like this ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we fail to realize that we are writing a set of instructions,  a computer is going to execute. Well a computer is a brain less machine. Yes it does not have a brain like you and me.
So any instruction given to a computer has to be step by step. It has to be logical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, we dont think like a computer. We think like human beings. The above logic when thought like a human, will work perfectly. Why ? we apparently apply a certain amount of logic on top of a logic. Yep ! Knowingly or unknowingly we do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I say the code is wrong to an interview candidate, I usually see this reaction in their face "Hey ! Hold on !! What is wrong with that code ?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple. That is when I say "Execute your logic for the first 20 numbers." Yep, you could try too. If you still get the output right for the first 20 number on the above code, again read up the second point I have talked about. "Think like a computer, not like a human being" .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you still get it right, dont worry , here is why it is wrong.
1. Lets take 3. The above code will print "Fizz" . Why ? The first if condition satisfies.
2. Lets take 5. The above code will print "Buzz". Why ? The second condition satisfies.
3. Lets take 15. Why 15 ? It is the first number divisible from both 3 and 5. The above code will print "FizzBuzz". Why ? The third condition satisfies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right ! Hey hold on ...! Something is fishy here.  The third condition .. Isint that wrong ?? Wouldnt that print "Fizz" instead of "FizzBuzz" ?
If this thought has come to you, yes you are right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets analyze a little more. What does an "if" statement do ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a condition is satisfied, it executes a set of instructions. Right ? Now for a moment lets think like machines and look at the above code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the number 15, lets run though the first condition. 15 is divisible by 3. Yes the condition is true. So it would print "Fizz". Thats it. That is how a machine works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is the difference between "Natural Human Language" and "Computer Language".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A computer can just execute instruction given by you and me. It does not have a brain by itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So without further delay, lets get to the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;FizzBuzz&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;elif&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Fizz&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;elif&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Buzz&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You see the re-arrangement in the logic ? Now run though the three numbers 3,5,15 and the code should work good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Psst ! Can you optimize the code a little more ?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is very simple. When a problem has an ambiguity in terms of condition, always double think the conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as always, when you write code&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always think like a computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="[interview"></category><category term="problem-solving"></category><category term="fizzbuzz]"></category></entry><entry><title>Building a Custom Centos 6.6 Respin</title><link href="/technology/2015/11/02/building-a-custom-centos-66-respin/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-11-02:technology/2015/11/02/building-a-custom-centos-66-respin/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a part of our work at Fractalio, we wanted to build a custom Cent- OS ISO, to be able to circulate it amongst people for them test and get a feel of what we are trying to build.  We had a trail once before and we had failed miserably building nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We build statues out of snow, and weep to see them melt. -- Walter Scott&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well we wanted to give it a shot again. This time with the previous learnings as our pillar. This time we started reading a lot more articles and links to first understand what is being talked about and have a clear picture of what is to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can't build a great building on a weak foundation. You must have a solid foundation if you're going to have a strong superstructure. -- Gordon B. Hinckley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article will share all the learning that I went through to actually get something working. So lets get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best Practices&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Span a virtual machine with centos - 6.6 minimal installed. So that if something goes wrong it dosent mess up your system&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pre-Requisites :&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A virtual machine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Centos 6.6 Minimal ISO&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internet or the packages (.rpm files) along with all the dependencies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A mind to be ready to expriment and learn :-)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Span out the virtual machine you installed with Centos and execute the following instructions. Each command will also be accompanied with the details of why it is done. If you find something wrong, please do let me know in the comments. So poweron your virtual machine and follow on&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1 . Initial Setup:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;yum -y install rsync yum-utils createrepo genisoimage  isomd5sum yum-downloadonly
  &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;  &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s2"&gt; - rsync to sync to actual iso to your re-spin&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s2"&gt; - createrepo to make a folder with special permission so that the installed recognises the rpm inside this folder&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s2"&gt; - genisoimage to generate the iso from the custom packages&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s2"&gt; - yum-downloadonly  is a yum plugin to only download the rpms and not actually install it&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s2"&gt; &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2 . Get the files required&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; /root
mkdir respin-centos

mount -o loop,ro /root/CentOS-6.6-x86_64-minimal.iso /mnt
rsync -av /mnt/ .

find . -name TRANS.TBL -exec rm -f &lt;span class="o"&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="se"&gt;\;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s2"&gt;- respin-centos is the folder where we will build our iso from&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s2"&gt;- mount is to actually mount the iso in some mount point so that you can access the files. This is in an assumption that you have copied the actual iso to the /root partitiion of the VM or the iso building machine.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s2"&gt;- rsync is needed because the cp sometimes dosent copy all the hidden files. files like .discinfo .treeinfo are missed when you do a cp -r . So we use rsync, which dosent differenciate between these files&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s2"&gt;- The last line removed the unwanted files. that file is unwanted.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3 . Get the packages you want to install.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be installing python-devel, python-pip and httpd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;yum install -y python-devel python-pip httpd --downloadonly --downloaddir /root/respin-centos/Packages/
&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s2"&gt;- Remember the yum-downloadonly ? we are actually doing it here. This will download the the rpms and the dependency rpms to the Packages folder.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4 . Test the rpms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we check the package we add in ISO above is require any dependencies.If require than we add  dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;rpm –initdb –dbpath /root/build/Packages/

rpm -ivh –test –dbpath /root/build/Packages/ /root/build/Packages/*.rpm
After using above &lt;span class="nb"&gt;command &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; output is as shown below than we need to resolve fail dependencies.

warning: /root/build/Packages/acl-2.2.49-6.el6.x86_64.rpm: Header V3 RSA/SHA1 Signature, key ID c105b9de: NOKEY
error: Failed dependencies:
/etc/mime.types is needed by httpd-2.2.15-26.el6.centos.x86_64
apr-util-ldap is needed by httpd-2.2.15-26.el6.centos.x86_64
httpd-tools &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; 2.2.15-26.el6.centos is needed by httpd-2.2.15-26.el6.centos.x86_64
libapr-1.so.0&lt;span class="o"&gt;()(&lt;/span&gt;64bit&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; is needed by httpd-2.2.15-26.el6.centos.x86_64
libaprutil-1.so.0&lt;span class="o"&gt;()(&lt;/span&gt;64bit&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; is needed by httpd-2.2.15-26.el6.centos.x86_64
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Do not worry about warning messages.Our focus is only on fail dependencies as shown above.We require to download failed dependencies.Using below command to check yum provides these dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;yum provides “*/etc/mime.types*”
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Once you download all  dependencies  once again run below command to check all dependencies downloaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;rpm -ivh –test –dbpath /root/build/Packages/ /root/build/Packages/*.rpm
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The log show  following texts if all dependencies downloaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;warning: /root/build/Packages/acl-2.2.49-6.el6.x86_64.rpm: Header V3 RSA/SHA1 Signature, key ID c105b9de: NOKEY
Preparing… &lt;span class="c"&gt;########################################### [100%]&lt;/span&gt;
installing package filesystem-2.4.30-3.el6.x86_64 needs 8KB on the /mnt filesystem.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5 . Repodata&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need a file called the comps.xml to actually get the iso to work. Follow the steps below to actually get the file&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;ls repodata/
34bae2d3c9c78e04ed2429923bc095005af1b166d1a354422c4c04274bae0f59-c6-minimal-x86_64.xml
490d05bedc0f8be64c5c26a3c2a804b817eec00fe42223d1fb856566fa248130-primary.xml.gz
5291f680f7b6afd2444e583202951977779200bc5a295922ef816a90476e493e-filelists.sqlite.bz2
6e147c9aea5bf4c0f1ba7ecf759ddd3a259003a7f12a5a74398c9f05d672573d-primary.sqlite.bz2
98678399cf20d3bcc860229b9a3ba5d99a4446e95947030d567113e412fcc412-filelists.xml.gz
ce2d698b9fb1413b668443e88835a0642cea8f387c7f25cc946f56dd93f109bb-c6-minimal-x86_64.xml.gz
dc720ad0a977caf5eb6dee0648c29e420a22e2f4277e099c925ee727de0735cd-other.sqlite.bz2
e0d5ad3bff4d0bd6ffd5037d6e76049b09c1d4f697445be6071d100f865a46f3-other.xml.gz
repomd.xml

gunzip repodata/ce2d698b9fb1413b668443e88835a0642cea8f387c7f25cc946f56dd93f109bb-c6-minimal-x86_64.xml.gz

ls repodata/
34bae2d3c9c78e04ed2429923bc095005af1b166d1a354422c4c04274bae0f59-c6-minimal-x86_64.xml
490d05bedc0f8be64c5c26a3c2a804b817eec00fe42223d1fb856566fa248130-primary.xml.gz
5291f680f7b6afd2444e583202951977779200bc5a295922ef816a90476e493e-filelists.sqlite.bz2
6e147c9aea5bf4c0f1ba7ecf759ddd3a259003a7f12a5a74398c9f05d672573d-primary.sqlite.bz2
98678399cf20d3bcc860229b9a3ba5d99a4446e95947030d567113e412fcc412-filelists.xml.gz
ce2d698b9fb1413b668443e88835a0642cea8f387c7f25cc946f56dd93f109bb-c6-minimal-x86_64.xml
dc720ad0a977caf5eb6dee0648c29e420a22e2f4277e099c925ee727de0735cd-other.sqlite.bz2
e0d5ad3bff4d0bd6ffd5037d6e76049b09c1d4f697445be6071d100f865a46f3-other.xml.gz
repomd.xml

mv repodata/ce2d698b9fb1413b668443e88835a0642cea8f387c7f25cc946f56dd93f109bb-c6-minimal-x86_64.xml repodata/comps.xml
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6 . Create the repo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;createrepo -u &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;media://`head -1 .discinfo`&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; -g repodata/comps.xml .
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7 . The Kickstart file&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ks file is very important. Refer to a sample kickstart file here (https://github.com/ramaseshan/respin-iso/centos-6.6-x86-64)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the reference kickstart, there would be two post sections. One with chroot and the other without chroot (nochroot).
The difference between the two is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to do some non root operations like copying files that just have to be present in the new iso they can be done through the nochroot stuff.  Things like, copy, untar, modifying conf files, sed, awk etc. Hold There is more readon.
How are we actually copying files is simple, there are 3 componenets involved here, the vmlinuz (the actual installer, /mnt/source, wehere the iso is mounted, and the /mnt/sysimage, where the installing system is mounted. Read the sameple ks file to see a live example)
Refer to the next section on where the to be copied files will be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you want root operations like useradd, chmod etc, do it in the post section with chroot on. **&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8 . How to copy files&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;root@localhost respin-centos&lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;# mkdir tar&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;root@localhost respin-centos&lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;# touch tar/test&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;root@localhost respin-centos&lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;# ls tar/&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;test&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now you can copy this tar folder like this in the nochroot section of the ks file&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;cp -r /mnt/source/tar /mnt/sysimage/opt/
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9 . isolinux&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;chmod &lt;span class="m"&gt;755&lt;/span&gt; isolinux/isolinux.cfg
&lt;span class="c"&gt;#modify the isolinux.cfg to make it work like this&lt;/span&gt;

default linux
prompt 0
timeout 600
display boot.msg
F1 boot.msg
F2 options.msg
F3 general.msg
F4 param.msg
F5 rescue.msg
label linux
kernel vmlinuz
append &lt;span class="nv"&gt;initrd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;initrd.img &lt;span class="nv"&gt;ks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;cdrom:/ks.cfg &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; Add this entry in this line &lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10 . Generate the iso&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;mkisofs -r -R -J -T -v -no-emul-boot &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
  -boot-load-size &lt;span class="m"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
  -boot-info-table &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
  -V &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;respin-centos&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
  -p &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Ramaseshan&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
  -A &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;respin-centos-build1&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
  -b isolinux/isolinux.bin &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
  -c isolinux/boot.cat &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
  -x &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;lost+found&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
  --joliet-long &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
  -o /tmp/boot.iso .

 89.86% &lt;span class="k"&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;, estimate finish Fri Oct &lt;span class="m"&gt;30&lt;/span&gt; 16:19:23 2015
 92.17% &lt;span class="k"&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;, estimate finish Fri Oct &lt;span class="m"&gt;30&lt;/span&gt; 16:19:23 2015
 94.47% &lt;span class="k"&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;, estimate finish Fri Oct &lt;span class="m"&gt;30&lt;/span&gt; 16:19:23 2015
 96.77% &lt;span class="k"&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;, estimate finish Fri Oct &lt;span class="m"&gt;30&lt;/span&gt; 16:19:23 2015
 99.08% &lt;span class="k"&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;, estimate finish Fri Oct &lt;span class="m"&gt;30&lt;/span&gt; 16:19:23 2015
Total translation table size: 77608
Total rockridge attributes bytes: 34111
Total directory bytes: 59914
Path table size&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bytes&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;: 112
Done with: The File&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;s&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;                             Block&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;s&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;    216770
Writing:   Ending Padblock                         Start Block 216852
Done with: Ending Padblock                         Block&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;s&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;    150
Max brk space used 63000
&lt;span class="m"&gt;217002&lt;/span&gt; extents written &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;423&lt;/span&gt; MB&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yay !! We have the iso now. No go span another VM and start testing it :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To invent an airplane is nothing. To build one is something. But to fly is everything.   -- Otto Lilienthal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More references :
Checkout my gitrepo : https://github.com/ramaseshan/respin-iso/centos-6.6-x86-64&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have  my ks file and the quick commands docs and also the reference links I had used. Incase if you feel, I have written too much and need the commands quick. :-)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[centos6.6"></category><category term="resping"></category><category term="custombuilds]"></category></entry><entry><title>Why did I decide to call myself "voidspace"</title><link href="/about/2015/11/01/why-did-i-decide-to-call-myself-voidspace/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-11-01:about/2015/11/01/why-did-i-decide-to-call-myself-voidspace/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not really any reason, but still trying to justify.....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having born in India, movies kinda create a craze in you. What always created a craze in me was that every actor in the movie started naming themselves after rajnikanth named hiself "SuperStar".
Espically the recent guy called himself "Twinkle Twinkle Little Star". Crazy set of people, but I couldnt save myself from that :-D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I had a list of names, the most of them I liked was "Turaco", a beautiful bird in the african regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But somehow , I always had this urge to learn new things, not just technlogy stuff, but open to a lot of things. So I though, I needed a word that conveys that I am open to anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then I just found the word voidspace intresting. What made it more intresting is the domain name,
.xyz, voidspace and .xyz went in well. It blended awesome :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So just went ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My email is null@voidspace.xyz (if you were wondering)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;null is a computer keyword meaning nothing, just empty :-D&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[me"></category><category term="myself"></category><category term="myname"></category><category term="nickname]"></category></entry><entry><title>When should we quit ?</title><link href="/life/2015/09/02/when-should-we-quit/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-09-02:life/2015/09/02/when-should-we-quit/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had been working on a project called &lt;a href="http://charcha.space"&gt;CHARCHA&lt;/a&gt;
, for quite sometime now. The aim of this project is not to reinvent something that already exists, rather combine a few tools to make a workflow better.  Before building thus product , I have to confess that I have worked for 2 other companies and NY present is the 3rd startup I am working for. In all these cases, I have failed a lot of times , even thought of quitting a lot if time.  But I never quit, tough I took my time to finish things, I always finished things. I never gave up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So great, why am I writing this article ??? A few days back one of the contributors of the project called me and asked "Should we stop working in the project". That question stuck to me hard. I was not able to answer it. I was quite and was (not) listening to him, and my mind went through a flash of incidents from my life. This article is a summary of those incidents that flashed my mind and my subsequent response to that person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The following us going to involve a lot of boring stories of my past. Do BEWARE . . . !&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said that, once I’ve decided to write a blog post, I never ask myself the question, ‘does anyone care about this?’ I do ask myself questions like ‘Could I improve this?’, ‘Could this be better?’, and ‘Are there useful takeaways in this?’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was born in a lower middle-class family, who state of next day's food was a question mark. Without the help of a few relatives and friends, our life would have been at stake. My cousin brother and sister paid most part of education and life. My college education was a loan. But without these struggles,I woulnd't have been an "ENGINEER" today. I always will remember this in my life. This gives a powerful overview of what my past was, so that my future would be to change someone with the same present into my present future. Basically create a value in someone's life, not with money, but with RIGHT EDUCATION.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had failed a lot of times in my life,never actually have seen success until my 8th std, I was not someone people would even like to know. But I had my first success in my 8th std (2005), when I was awarded the "Yuva Kala Bharathi Award", as the youngest sanskrit teacher, who has though sanskrit to more than 100 people. To me then, it didnt really sound so great, I didnt even realize what I was doing. I just loved teaching. It was my passion. My influence to teaching comes from various teachers in my school and some special classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My 10std, result was a decent 80% from a CBSE board. I was quite happy the last 3 years. People actually talked to me. People included me in their sports team. They took me all they to district level matches for football, volleyball, shuttle. Teachers used to call me on stage, and sometimes my friends used to clap for me. It was quite amusing to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then life took that turn. A turn that gave me nothing but failures, until recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with a 80% score, I was rejected a higher education seat in my own school, most private schools, asked for money that we couldn't afford, and we had stand right outside the principal's room asking for a seat, just to be rejected saying you cant afford us. One of my school teachers(Late M/s Krishnambal Sanskrit teacher) told me, that she would talk to the principal and let me know. With some preassure and some support from a few teachers, I made it back to my old school. Tough I wasn't the same as before. I was given some responsibilities for managing my house (If you know what houses, in schools are.). I was not able to do it great, I was not able to be different. I was included in sports team, just to be rejected in the final moments.Friends used to talk less to me. With a mixed feeling of "Am I a nothing now ?" to "I can do something like 2005", I ended up being the former. I became a nothing at the end of my 12th std. I was soon forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to again cry for a college seat. We again couldn't afford a Management seat. And I had to go to karaikal.My College was no different, and neither was I trained to be different. I had to just be a mediacore person, who does nothing different but the same things, that everybody was ordered to do."I was not trained to be different, rather I was trained to be no different". I couldnt do it. I had backlogs. I failed in my most fav papers. I was not able to do assignment. I soon became the laughing stock of my class. Just more depressed. Just more failures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until my final year in college, thanks to a few juniors (Selva ganesh, Mohit jain and Lalith kumar), I had a chance of revival. I had an national level project contest, which I decided to participate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"For a long time I’ve been cursed with an inflated sense of my own potential but nothing to show for it. Nobody else agrees with me that I’m capable of amazing things because they haven’t seen any proof. I don’t need any more proof than what’s in my head, but others do—and rightly so.So I need to prove. I need a proof for myself."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to do it. After bunking a lot of classes, We finished this project, and we won the 3rd prize. It meant something for me.I had revived. People again recognized me. People talked to me. But very soon, it went in vain. Again disheartned. I learnt this world needs success. A success which they see as success, to exist in a person for them to talk to, to value them, to even include them in their life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awaiting more events to success, I just ended up getting hired for a company that doesent exist. I couldnt live there. I decided, I will go to Bangalore. I will search for a job.
Roaming roads after roads, dropping my resumes in every company I see with a computer, used to happed everyday for a month. But one thing remained. FAILURE. I never even got a call, if at all I got one, that seat would be reserved with somebody with a reference. Until one fine week, I was hired my two companies, one from chennai and one from bangalore. For all stupid reasons in the world, I decided to join the Bangalore company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I joined IdeaPlunge in Sept, 2013, as an intern. The first day I landed in that company,I was handed a single man project to be completed with Java Stuts as the backend, and backbone.js as the front end. They were alien to me. I had to learn a lot. I could wait around until I’ve improved my skills and learned more and studied how the pros get things done. But I might never be convinced that I’m ready (sound familiar?). So I had to started working before I was ready. I couldn't handle the workload. I used to work 18*7 (yes, 18 hours a day, 7 days a week.). The company told they are not satisfied with me.Everyday it was the same statement I used to hear, when I updated my status at 12 in night to my manager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was wanting a challenge, A challenge was given. but I still couldnt prove myself. I stated thinking, what is wrong. But then people working along with me also had the same response. We all quit the company the same day, just to be jobless again. Roaming, dropping resumes, getting rejected, became common again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was a member of the Free Software moment, then, but without really knowing anything about Free Software. I never really invested time in learning about it. One of my friends (Prasanna Venkatesh), offered me an iternship in chennai, but then I really didn't want to go back to my past. So , I stopped and looked back in my life. Apart from the two success,I never really had anything. I wasn't the smart programmer, I didnt really try anything different in my life, only thing that was different, was the failures I had in life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that thought, really didn't have an impact in my life. I just joined another company in bangalore as an intern again. I was paid a little more, but thenI could harldy manage myself and nothing more. But the two months of internship created a thought in me. But this time, I took time. I learnt the tools, I was going to work with. I was not very efficient, but I could get the job done, in my own time (not the deadlines set to me). That is when I started exploring more. I started learning everything I saw. My roommate (Rajesh Kumar), was a person, who created a change in my life. He streamlined my technical skills. I was at a stage when I used to ask the basic question to him to , solve some problems, that he told "Good", for. I meant something to me. I was improving. I started writing code for everything I started seeing. I started thinking differently. I went from a not even a decent programmer, to a programmer, who can code any average problem with the help of internet and in my own time. I realized one thing then. I started working on some project ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So with all going good, life was probably not happy with me being happy. It gave the twist again. This time, the startup I worked for, shutdown. Rejection (My best friend) was back. This time, I had just worked for an year. I was not very bad, but I was a decent programmer. I really didnt want to join an MNC. I realized in one year, I had grown to a decent level. I needed this growth. But this time with no job, I was not applying to any job. I rather decided to start my own start-up. I had no experience. I had no expections either. I just needed something, that will make me belive me in myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I have had a 1000 failures before, what is 1 more going to make a difference ?". This was my thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had an idea, I started working on the prototype along with my roommate and ex-officemate (Harish), to get the prototype successfully completed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"To keep creating without falling into existential disarray I’ve learned to be brave and start from a base assumption that if I care about my work at least one other person probably does too, so it’s worth finishing."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prototype was live. We were happy. We now took the prototype out for validation. People were exited to look at a product like ours. But then the hard question came, what is our revenue model. The obvious answer that came was "Data and pattern collection and selling them". Everybody accepted it. I started reading more on that. I took the responsibility of the buisness side of it. I was pretty impressed with "Data as the revenue model". It works. That is when, the Free software movement came into play in my life, to create another failure. I read about survillence and decided not to have "Data collection" as the revenue model. I just felt it was against the ethics of a common man. We cant sell a common man's data to companies all over the world. My team-mates were not happy. We got an investor call. He was also impressed with the idea, and asked the same old question. "What is the revenue model ?". I didnt have an answer. I replied "I am working on it." He was ok, but then he put a condition, atleast two people should sit full time. I came back happy, and told my other two people. But then for the life's twist again, both of them told a "NO", for full time, and the investor was not happy with one person, coding and handling the buisness.
Things dropped off again. It went from an interesting idea to a nothing. All that happiness was just to go in vain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was back to the job search. This time I improvised. Instead of dropping resume's in person, I dropped in emails, just to see no different response. I took me 4 months of joblessness to realize, I had become a nothing again. I kept attending interviews, I kept taking calls, I kept trying. Until at one point, I was selected for a a few companies. But this time, I decided to join a company that is inclined with my values (Free Software, Free society). I found one.I joined Fractalio Data, as an engineer. This time, I invested more time, learning than coding. I didnt code random stuff. I read more, and wrote a more clear code. I kept improving. I wrote better code. I became better. Its been 8 months working here, and I spent, 80% of my time, reading about the work I do, than code the work. The moment I am clear with job I am going to do, I do the job better. But apart from doing the job, this time I was doing a job with some values, that I belive in. For good or bad, I am paid less than most of you people out there, but then I am improving. That is enough for me. Afterall moeny is just one more entity in our life. It is not the only thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I became more associated with some Free Software societies, I learnt a lot and read a lot. With all interactions I have with people, I look for problem that technology can solve. Sometimes solutions already exists, sometimes they are split up, sometimes they dont.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charcha is one such expriment, which came up to solve the problem of community discussions. Distributed solutions exist, but then, there was no unified solution. So Charcha, basically took a few technologies (WebRTC, Etherpad) and gave a platform to have discussion and note taking simultaneously. It is not a different product, but is a product with a difference. There is nothing new is what people feel, but when you merge two technologies, and have to make them work is sync, is the actual challenge. And when it is a web product, the work of optimizing it for a lower bandwidth consumption is another bigger challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all these thoughts, that flased my mind, I told, We are not stopping working on Charcha. I told, there are real world use-cases, when this tool cal be used. And I am not quitting it. Its the choice of other people, to choose to quit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"If someone asks me whether anyone cares about what I’m working on, I can usually tell them honestly that I’d read this if someone else wrote it, or I’d use this app if someone else built it.I’m always working in-line with my values."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well to answer the question of the article,"When to quit" ?
Quit when necessary, not when you cant. When you cant, postpond it.You can eventually come back to it and solve it. I had a lot of reasons to quit, but I never did. I just keep going, tough I cant solve problem at your pace, I can always solve it at my own pace. Eventually I will solve it. But I never quit trying. I never quit, the thirst for knowledge and knowing. Life is all about learning, and keep going forward.There is no stopping. There is no quitting. You just dis-align with things that dosent suit your values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But always remember :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We all start in the same place: no money, no resources, no contacts, no experience. The difference is that some people — the winners — choose to start anyway.” James Clear&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in contributing to charcha, please do write to us.
&lt;a href="mailto:hello@charcha.space"&gt;hello@charcha.space&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could follow charcha here : &lt;a href="https://github.com/charcha"&gt;https://github.com/charcha&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[life"></category><category term="thoughts"></category><category term="quitting"></category><category term="when-to-quit]"></category></entry><entry><title>IT life and a remote village</title><link href="/life/2015/08/15/it-life-and-a-remote-village/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-08-15:life/2015/08/15/it-life-and-a-remote-village/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Everybody has dreams in life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Part 1 : History&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike every engineering graduate, I also wanted to work for an IT company, earn money and lead a happy life. I was trained to be "No Different from others" in life, work etc. I was not that super cool programmer who would say "I would write code that will convert caffine to coffee". I was an average programmer.And since I had a lot of downs right from when I started my carrer. I was also associated to a Non-Profit Organization called FSHM - Free Software Hardware Movement, Pondicherry (a part of FSFTN) right from my late college days (though I was not too much involved).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this background, I came to bangalore and joined an Internship. Didnt quite go well, I was never able to make it up to their expectation. Joined another firm for a job. Learned a lot, but never actually did something I liked. I was building a solution, without even know, If the problem the company stated was a really a problem. Quit the job again. For 4 months I didn't think of taking up a job, I started exploring various things in my life. That is when I really got a little more active with organizatations like FSFTN, various tech and startup groups in Facebook. These 4 months changed the way I live, my thoughts, my thinking. I interacted with a lot of unknown people, talked on various things. Though my roommate and all my relatives used to persistently keep saying "Throw all these thoughts and find a job man", I somehow didnt quite feel that is right. People referred me to various companies, I just didn't find "do something to fill your stomach and shut the mouth of the society" quite right too. I would call these 4 months the most progressive ME ever. I went all the way from working in a 9-6 job, to start a startup(tough I failed with a lot of learning) and back to nothing. In the end, the society was right. I was out of money, the feeling of getting frustrated was more. I really wanted a job. I wanted to go back to the 9-6 life. I finally realized to really do something different,you also want to be sorrounded with like minded people. Else you just have that negative mentality sorrounding you, which will make you feel like you are dumb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started attending interviews. One after one, I failed,I didnt make it. Finally days came, when calls also stopped. I was clueless what to do. My mom was sick, I went to trichy.I felt it was better to take care of mom in these times, also didnt quite really have a job to do.I stayed with her in the hospital. "Nobody else in this world can give you more positive thoughts than your mom". Tough I was getting positive, what bothered me was, I was not even able to pay a small medicine bill to my mom on my own. I had become dependent on my dad, relatives... "Is this all why I graduated as an engineer ? To be a nothing."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the thought that was in me. My good luck, I got 3 calls the week I stayed with my mom. And this I decided I have to crack them. Went back to bangalore, and the first interview was a failure. I didnt know what else to do except sitting in the room and cry (tough I didnt get tears :-D). That is when my roommate told "You cant crack every interview. There are interviews meant for you. Learn from your mistakes, and give the next interview a better shot".
I did, and I made it to a company called Fractalio Data. Cracked the next interview too. Now I really had to take a call in which company I had to join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my interview with fractalio, the founders hinted me saying they just didnt wanted to be an IT company and they will move the company to a small village called Taggachguppe. Plus, this was not a typical web development firm. They were working with "Data Storage systems", actually they were building one. For a long time I have been using and talking about GNU/Linux, and here was a real chance, that will let me really work on it. So I went ahead and joined them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Part 2 : Geography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its been 6 months now me working at Fractalio, and we just moved into an extremely remote village called Taggachguppe, in Magadi Road. It is adventure here everyday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Place&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its a beautiful place, fully sorrounded by hills, trees, cows, hens, peococks. Its a  beautiful natural scenary every morning. We can see the clouds kissing the mountains, peacocks making their beautiful noise, hens waking us up every morning.To walk from our stay to office, we come down a cement roaded hill. Every where around is a agricultural farm. You can also see some people crazy for money, bomb the hills every evening to get stones off,gun sounds killing animals (though I dont know where they shoot them). Hardly any mobile signals, I feel like mostly off the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The People&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poeple are mostly from agricultural,carpentary etc background here. Technology has influenced the people here only to the extent of a TV and basic mobile phones (hardly any smart phones). I havent heard of people having a computer here. Poeple mostly are dependent on daily wages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being in a place like this, and running an IT company is not as easy as running it in a Urban Center. I did not complete the whole stuff, but we are already working there, and we are having plans of making sure the people there are also thought. We havent started anything in that front yet, but we have plans, concrete ones. We will soon start out doing out one by one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have read the blog till this point, you are surely interested in what we are doing. It are an IT guy, loves GNU/Linux, and also interested in hacking a few out of IT like agriculture, improvising the state of agriculture, lets talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psst ! We are still hiring. If you are interested or got interesting ideas, drop me a mail : ramaseshan@fractalio.com or ram.seshan.cs@gmail.com&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[life"></category><category term="thoughts"></category><category term="work"></category><category term="rural_working]"></category></entry><entry><title>SaltStack and Python</title><link href="/technology/2015/04/02/saltstack-and-python/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-04-02:technology/2015/04/02/saltstack-and-python/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;SaltStack is a infrastructure management tool, that is scalable ( can manage up to thousands of servers ) and written in python. Salt also does a lot of remote execution and configuration management too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official docs can be found here : http://docs.saltstack.com/en/latest/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is going to talk about how to use SaltStack with python. We at Fractalio Data, heavily rely on SaltStack for various operations. We basically build Data Storage Servers, and we want to regulary keep package updates running on all the servers, manage configurations, get status and resource utiliation of each individual nodes, restart services incase of failures, transfer log and other files between nodes and more. Apart from the development team, our testing team is completely automated using SaltStack. We have automated the test suite for one server, and same test suite is executed on all the servers parallely and the final results and gathered from all the servers and mined for all useful data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will discuss a basic usage of SaltStack with python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pre-requisites :
    1. You should have installed Salt master and have atleast one salt minion.
    2. You should have received the minion request on the master (not necessarily accepted)
    3. You should be the root user or the user who has access to salt. It will be defined in the master config (/etc/salt/master grep for user)
    4. This code has to be run on the same machine as Salt master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open the terminal and go to the python console typing python&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will use the Salt wheel client to accept the minions. Wheels are used for interating with various parts of salt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will get all the pending minions to be accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;salt.wheel&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;opts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;salt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;master_config&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;/etc/salt/master&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c"&gt;#The path of your salt master configuration&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;wheel&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;salt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;wheel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Wheel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;opts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c"&gt;# Initialize the wheel with various salt opts&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;keys&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;wheel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;call_func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;key.list_all&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;  
&lt;span class="n"&gt;pending_minions&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;keys&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;minions_pre&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pending_minions&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;and this code would accept it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;m&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pending_minions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;try&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;wheel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;call_func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;key.accept&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;match&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;%s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;m&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)):&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Error accepting Minion key for &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;%s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt; &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;m&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;except&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ne"&gt;Exception&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Error accepting Minion key for &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;%s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt; : &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;%s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;m&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Viola ! And you are done accepting the minions. Lets first test if the minions are accepted properly and explore more on what the above code is doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;python&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;salt.client&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;salt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;LocalClient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;cmd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;*&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;test.ping&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;Seshan@fractalio&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c"&gt;# Yay, the minion has responded.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So lets now explore more of what the above code is doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first code block, we had these lines :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;keys&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;wheel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;call_func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;key.list_all&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;  
&lt;span class="n"&gt;pending_minions&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;keys&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;minions_pre&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The keys variable will contain all the keys that the salt master contains. Irrespective of if they are accepted or not accpeted or rejected, the keys variable will contain all the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pending_minions will contain all the not accepted minions. Why is called minions_pre, why not minions_pending ?? Do an &lt;strong&gt; ls /etc/salt/pki/master/ &lt;/strong&gt; , and you will figure out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second code block :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;wheel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;call_func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;key.accept&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;match&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;%s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;m&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The above code says the wheel client to passes 'accept' request and the minion key as an argument to the call_func. The whole if condition and the and try blocks are basic python to safely handle the failed cases and etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have got the basic hello world working. Now lets explore more on this, shall we.
 Read more here.  ramaseshan.github.io/technology/2015/04/02/saltstack-and-python-more-operations/&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[technology"></category><category term="saltstack"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="saltapi"></category><category term="salt-basics]"></category></entry><entry><title>SaltStack and Python- More Operations</title><link href="/technology/2015/04/02/saltstack-and-python-more-operations/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-04-02:technology/2015/04/02/saltstack-and-python-more-operations/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post talks about doing various operations using SaltStack and Python. If you are looking for the basics, please refer here. ramaseshan.github.io/technology/2015/04/02/saltstack-and-python/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A basic ls command example&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;salt.client&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;salt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;LocalClient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;cmd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;*&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;cmd.run&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;ls&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;and the output would be :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;{&amp;#39;Seshan@fractalio&amp;#39;: &amp;#39;Desktop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;Documents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;Downloads&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;Music&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;Pictures&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;Public&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;Templates&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;Videos&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;test&amp;#39;}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What does the above code do ?
The above code in the terminal is executed as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;salt&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;*&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cmd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;run&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ls&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lets look at the various components of the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;LocalClient&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;object&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;\*&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;--&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tells&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;target&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;this&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;command&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;at&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;all&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;minions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;You&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;can&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;replace&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;things&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;like&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;192.168.1.20\*&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;which&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;will&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;target&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;all&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;minions&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;key&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;This&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;called&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;gobbling&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;SaltStack&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;also&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;supports&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;regular&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;expressions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cmd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;run&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;--&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;this&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;salt&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;module&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;that&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;used&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;run&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;command&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;terminal&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;get&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;specified&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;client.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Eg&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="nn"&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;other&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;modules&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;test&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ping&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;state&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;highstate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;etc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;ls&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;parameter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;or&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;command&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;that&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;be&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;passed&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cmd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;run&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Other&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;examples&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;are&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;service network restart&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;or&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;any&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;command&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;that&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;execute&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;can&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;be&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;parameter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So what happens when you want to pass a parameter to ls ?? then you can say ,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;cmd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;*&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;cmd.run&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;ls&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;/tmp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most of the things you can accomplish by the above, but have a list of all the available modules in saltstack here : http://docs.saltstack.com/en/latest/ref/modules/all/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sure you would have also heard about grains in SaltStack.
If you want to target minions by the grains, then here is what you have to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;cmd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;roles:primary&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;cmd.run&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;ls&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;expr_form&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;grain&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So instead of using '*', we use the grain key and value, and say explicitly that the expr_form='grain'.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[technology"></category><category term="saltstack"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="saltapi"></category><category term="salt-operations]"></category></entry><entry><title>Document Freedom Day Talk at Fractalio Data</title><link href="/free-society/2015/03/25/document-freedom-day-talk-at-fractalio-data/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-03-25:free-society/2015/03/25/document-freedom-day-talk-at-fractalio-data/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We were happy to celebrate Document Freedom Day 2015 at Fractalio Data. We had a small talk titled  "What is Document Freedom and Why should I care about it". We had about 20 people working in our shared offices come in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Event Report :  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;25 March 2015 organized by &lt;br /&gt;
Event: Open Talk &lt;br /&gt;
Date: 25 March 2015 from 11:00 to 11:45  &lt;br /&gt;
Place: Fractalio Data shared office space.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About the Talk: &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This DFD was celebrated along with the birthday of our colluege Ms.Prathiba. We had a cake cutting (for the birthday) which was followed a talk by Ramaseshan.S, along with Kiran Patil, Naveen and Raghuram who are a part of Engineering Team at Fractalio Data. A special thanks to be given to Pradeed of Data Lifecycle Company for helping us get organized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk basically focussed on the following topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is a document&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defination of Freedom in documents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why should you be worried if the non-free documents and what are the document standards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why should you also be a part of Document Freedom movement and start using document standsrds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few examples of open document standards like IP, Libre Office etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Image gallery&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id="dfd_images"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-24%2016.18.29.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-24%2016.19.09.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-24%2016.20.25.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-24%2016.20.38.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.15.47.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.16.02.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.21.59.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.22.29.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.22.40.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.23.54.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.25.17.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.31.51.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We would like to thank Ms. Sangeetha for organising the event and the participants, and the DatalifeCycle Company for the space. Greater thanks to Ms. Prathiba for allowing us to celebrate DFD along with her birthday. Thanks to all the participants for attending.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A special thanks for Free Software Foundation Tamilnadu(FSFTN http://fsftn.org/) and FSF (Free Software Foundation), for the stickers and swags that we used for distributing to the participants. We would also like to thank all the contributers in the Free and Open world, without whom this whole talk would not have been possible.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[free-society"></category><category term="document-freedom-day"></category><category term="dfd2015"></category><category term="opentalk ]"></category></entry><entry><title>Free Internet Awareness at Fractalio Data and Data Lifecycle Company in Bangalore</title><link href="/free-society/2015/03/22/free-internet-awareness-at-fractalio-data-and-data-lifecycle-company-in-bangalore/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-03-22:free-society/2015/03/22/free-internet-awareness-at-fractalio-data-and-data-lifecycle-company-in-bangalore/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The office we work at is a shared space, comprising of a Storage Integrator company called &lt;a href="http://www.datalifecycle.in/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The DatalifeCycle Company&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and a Travel company called &lt;a href="http://earthwalk.co.in/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EarthWalk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.fractalio.com"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fractalio Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (That's us). Most people working in all these 3 places have been using GNU/Linux, without understanding the philosophy behind using GNU/Linux. The engineering team at Fractalio Data, were a set of Free Software enthusiasts and we thought we should make people aware of the reason behind why GNU/Linux exists and they are not using it just because it was available for a zero cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a first step, we started with the topic Free Internet. So why did you talk about Free Internet when you concept was Free Software. The reason was, the people here were from various background, and for them understand the concept of privacy and the real reason why free software need to exist, would be a little hard to understand. So we just thought we would introduce them to the privacy issues of the internet, which might actually help them to understand the underlying problem, and them with a series of talks we could move towards a fully free software or rather towards a free society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk, we basically introduced them to what is Internet, what are big corporations, and how each of them are trying to control the internet that we use. Talking on corporate and government survilence, and also exposing them to a few things that facebook and google does with the data that they collect. The talk went
on showing a few real usecases on how our data is being misused for more personalised advertisments, talking examples of flipkart.com and myntra.com ad's , and also a basic overview of facebook and google's ad mechanism. The talk ended suggesting them a few alternatives to the basic internet application they use, and ended with a QA session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation I had used is available to download here.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href="/files/Free-Internet.odp" class="btn btn-success"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download the presentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
The presentation also contains notes for each slide, referring what links the people can refer to understand more about what each slide talked about. The slide is also to be circulated to everybody who works at all these offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psst ! To view the notes, download and open the presentation in Libre Office, and click on notes in the slide view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Image gallery&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/1.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/2.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/3.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/7.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/4.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/5.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/6.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/8.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Next Steps:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;* We have decided to short talks in more decentralised small groups,
in helping them get started with better internet tools, like DuckDuckGo, Diaspora, Cryptocat etc.
* We have decided to create small office level groups on Telegram,
so people would not complain , none of my friends are on telegram, so why should I use it.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A special thanks for Free Software Foundation Tamilnadu(FSFTN http://fsftn.org/), for the stickers and swags that we used for distributing to the participants.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note : Feel free to add more notes to the presentation and share it back, so that we can use the knowledge and information that we have missed and you have, to share amongst ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[free-society"></category><category term="free-internet"></category><category term="]"></category></entry><entry><title>About Me</title><link href="/about/2015/01/15/about-me/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-01-15:about/2015/01/15/about-me/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;About Me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A storage engineer and DevOps by profession, from India, who loves woking on GNU/Linux, Python and Shell. Free Software, Free Internet and a Free Knowledge Enthusiast.
I also love promoting "Fedora + Free Software in Education".
&lt;br /&gt;Apart from the Digital world, I love exploring on Renewable Energy and a Nature lover. Sanskrit as a language has also always been my passion.
&lt;br /&gt; Loves teaching on a condition that , &lt;strong&gt;Learn Free and Teach back Free&lt;/strong&gt;.
And ya, if you were wondering , my codes live at my &lt;a href="https://github.com/ramaseshan"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Talks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I talk at colleges on Free Software, Adoption of Free Software in Education and "Programming in Python".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My previous talks include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction to Python @ Shanmuganathan enginering college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is Free Software and Free Software in Education @ Tamil Virtual Academy, Salem&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction to Free Software @ Alagapa University, Karaikudi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer : I am working on listing it all out. Listing only the recent ones. Missed out the presentations used in previous talks. Once I find them will add them to my &lt;a href="voidspace.xyz/presentations"&gt;presentations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About my workstation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I run Fedora GNU/Linux 23 (the cinnamon spin :-D ). Free Software user in most of the tools.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; My God-mode is Tmux + ZSH + Oh-my-zsh + vim. &lt;/strong&gt;
I sometimes use Atom Editor tough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the sticker I use in my laptop &lt;a href="https://github.com/ramaseshan/sticker-project/blob/master/Final/Free_Software_Fedora.png"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My servers runs, CentOS 6.6, if you were wondering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/"&gt; Home&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="mailto:null@voidspace.xyz"&gt;Drop me a line&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>My Projects</title><link href="/about/2015/01/15/my-projects/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-01-15:about/2015/01/15/my-projects/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;List of projects I am currently working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work in Progress. Behold ...!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>