<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>My life rants</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/free-society.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2016-01-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Using Pelican to deploy static website in Gitlab.</title><link href="/free-society/2015/12/23/using-pelican-to-deploy-static-website-in-gitlab/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-01-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-12-23:free-society/2015/12/23/using-pelican-to-deploy-static-website-in-gitlab/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I my last article I wrote about gitlab pages.
This article is a quick note on how to deploy your static blog using pelican.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is a more developer /  computer known person prespective. If something goes wrong do ping me&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steps :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sign up for an account at gitlab.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new project called blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the GNU/Linux terminal and follow the steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sudo dnf install python-pip (Fedora) or sudo apt-get install python-pip (Debian)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sudo pip install virtualenv&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cd ~/Documents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git clone https://gitlab.com/your_username/blog.git&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;virtualenv blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cd blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;source bin activate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pip install pelican markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pelican-quickstart .Once you hit this command,enter the details of your site name and description. Go with the defaults for the rest of the things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cd content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create a file called first-blog.md (or any name). Write content following this pattern http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.6.3/content.html&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cd ../&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;type the command "pelican" . Once this command is done, you should have a folder called output. If that has generated, proceed, else hold up and cross check any errors or missed steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create a file called .gitlab-ci.yml and enter the following contents in it.
"""
pages:
  stage: deploy
  script:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mkdir .public&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cp -r output/* .public&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mv .public public
  artifacts:
    paths:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;public
  only:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;master
"""&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git add .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git commit -m "Blog on gitlab"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git push&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are done. If all go good, you should see the build starting in your projects build page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now sit back and relax until the build completes. Once done, you should see your website live at your-username.gitlab.io/blog&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for a ready repo, have a look at the &lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/voidspacexyz/pages/tree/master"&gt;sample repo&lt;/a&gt; I have put up&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have a sample blog running &lt;a href="http://voidspacexyz.gitlab.io/pages"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have written it better, send me a PR :-)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[free-society"></category><category term="gitlab"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="static_website]"></category></entry><entry><title>Static Websites on Gitlab</title><link href="/free-society/2015/12/23/static-websites-on-gitlab/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-01-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-12-23:free-society/2015/12/23/static-websites-on-gitlab/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Most of you might have been using a website called github.com for hosting your code repos. For those of you who dont know what is github, it is basically a website that offers, a version control system. Github also offers free unlimited "public" code hosting. And then if you want private code hosting, you have to pay and use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great so what is wrong with github.com now.
It is a simple answer. github is not a free software. If you dont know what is a free software, read about it &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.en.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.fsf.org/about/what-is-free-software"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why should I care if a hosted service is a free software or not ?
Simple, "Free Software requires Free Tools". More about it &lt;a href="https://mako.cc/writing/hill-free_tools.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon some research, I came across something called &lt;a href="https://gitlab.com"&gt;Gitlab&lt;/a&gt;. Gitlab is a free software, both in terms of code and in terms of hosting. We can have our own hosted version of the code or simply take the code and deploy it in our own servers. And another amazing thing I felt about gitlab was, it has taken some of the best features of github, bitbucket , gitorious etc and put them all together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for a long time, I have been missing one of the best features of github. It is called github-pages. It was the only reason I really didnt want to move out of github, if any of my project needed a website ? I didnt have the resource to host a website on a paid service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But alas to my happiness , gitlab on 22-Dec introduced gitlab-pages to its EE. So which meant, gitlab.com will have gitlab pages, where I could run website for my projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some more links, where you can find the official documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://doc.gitlab.com/ee/pages/README.html"&gt;Gitlab Pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/gitlab-examples/pages-plain-html"&gt;Writing plain html to deploy websites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/gitlab-examples/pages-plain-html"&gt;using jekyll to deploy sites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a python person, and already in love with pelican, &lt;a href="/free-society/2015/12/23/introducing-gitlab-pages/," title="link"&gt;go ahead here&lt;/a&gt; to use pelican to deploy your blog.
Belive me pelican is a much better tool then jekyll. Here is a article from @arunrocks justifying &lt;a href="http://arunrocks.com/moving-blogs-to-pelican/"&gt;why pelican&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now go ahead and explore Gitlab at gitlab.com&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[free-society"></category><category term="gitlab"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="static_website]"></category></entry><entry><title>Document Freedom Day Talk at Fractalio Data</title><link href="/free-society/2015/03/25/document-freedom-day-talk-at-fractalio-data/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-01-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-03-25:free-society/2015/03/25/document-freedom-day-talk-at-fractalio-data/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We were happy to celebrate Document Freedom Day 2015 at Fractalio Data. We had a small talk titled  "What is Document Freedom and Why should I care about it". We had about 20 people working in our shared offices come in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Event Report :  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;25 March 2015 organized by &lt;br /&gt;
Event: Open Talk &lt;br /&gt;
Date: 25 March 2015 from 11:00 to 11:45  &lt;br /&gt;
Place: Fractalio Data shared office space.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About the Talk: &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This DFD was celebrated along with the birthday of our colluege Ms.Prathiba. We had a cake cutting (for the birthday) which was followed a talk by Ramaseshan.S, along with Kiran Patil, Naveen and Raghuram who are a part of Engineering Team at Fractalio Data. A special thanks to be given to Pradeed of Data Lifecycle Company for helping us get organized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk basically focussed on the following topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is a document&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defination of Freedom in documents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why should you be worried if the non-free documents and what are the document standards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why should you also be a part of Document Freedom movement and start using document standsrds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few examples of open document standards like IP, Libre Office etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Image gallery&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id="dfd_images"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-24%2016.18.29.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-24%2016.19.09.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-24%2016.20.25.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-24%2016.20.38.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.15.47.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.16.02.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.21.59.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.22.29.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.22.40.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.23.54.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.25.17.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/theme/images/dfd-images/2015-03-25%2011.31.51.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We would like to thank Ms. Sangeetha for organising the event and the participants, and the DatalifeCycle Company for the space. Greater thanks to Ms. Prathiba for allowing us to celebrate DFD along with her birthday. Thanks to all the participants for attending.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A special thanks for Free Software Foundation Tamilnadu(FSFTN http://fsftn.org/) and FSF (Free Software Foundation), for the stickers and swags that we used for distributing to the participants. We would also like to thank all the contributers in the Free and Open world, without whom this whole talk would not have been possible.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[free-society"></category><category term="document-freedom-day"></category><category term="dfd2015"></category><category term="opentalk ]"></category></entry><entry><title>Free Internet Awareness at Fractalio Data and Data Lifecycle Company in Bangalore</title><link href="/free-society/2015/03/22/free-internet-awareness-at-fractalio-data-and-data-lifecycle-company-in-bangalore/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-01-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Voidspace</name></author><id>tag:,2015-03-22:free-society/2015/03/22/free-internet-awareness-at-fractalio-data-and-data-lifecycle-company-in-bangalore/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The office we work at is a shared space, comprising of a Storage Integrator company called &lt;a href="http://www.datalifecycle.in/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The DatalifeCycle Company&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and a Travel company called &lt;a href="http://earthwalk.co.in/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EarthWalk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.fractalio.com"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fractalio Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (That's us). Most people working in all these 3 places have been using GNU/Linux, without understanding the philosophy behind using GNU/Linux. The engineering team at Fractalio Data, were a set of Free Software enthusiasts and we thought we should make people aware of the reason behind why GNU/Linux exists and they are not using it just because it was available for a zero cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a first step, we started with the topic Free Internet. So why did you talk about Free Internet when you concept was Free Software. The reason was, the people here were from various background, and for them understand the concept of privacy and the real reason why free software need to exist, would be a little hard to understand. So we just thought we would introduce them to the privacy issues of the internet, which might actually help them to understand the underlying problem, and them with a series of talks we could move towards a fully free software or rather towards a free society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk, we basically introduced them to what is Internet, what are big corporations, and how each of them are trying to control the internet that we use. Talking on corporate and government survilence, and also exposing them to a few things that facebook and google does with the data that they collect. The talk went
on showing a few real usecases on how our data is being misused for more personalised advertisments, talking examples of flipkart.com and myntra.com ad's , and also a basic overview of facebook and google's ad mechanism. The talk ended suggesting them a few alternatives to the basic internet application they use, and ended with a QA session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation I had used is available to download here.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href="/files/Free-Internet.odp" class="btn btn-success"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download the presentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
The presentation also contains notes for each slide, referring what links the people can refer to understand more about what each slide talked about. The slide is also to be circulated to everybody who works at all these offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psst ! To view the notes, download and open the presentation in Libre Office, and click on notes in the slide view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Image gallery&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/1.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/2.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/3.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/7.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/4.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/5.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/6.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Alt image" src="/theme/images/free-internet-images/8.jpg" title="Free-Internet Talk Images" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Next Steps:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;* We have decided to short talks in more decentralised small groups,
in helping them get started with better internet tools, like DuckDuckGo, Diaspora, Cryptocat etc.
* We have decided to create small office level groups on Telegram,
so people would not complain , none of my friends are on telegram, so why should I use it.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A special thanks for Free Software Foundation Tamilnadu(FSFTN http://fsftn.org/), for the stickers and swags that we used for distributing to the participants.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note : Feel free to add more notes to the presentation and share it back, so that we can use the knowledge and information that we have missed and you have, to share amongst ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="[free-society"></category><category term="free-internet"></category><category term="]"></category></entry></feed>